Guide to the George Pólya Papers SC0337
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
George Pólya papers
1884-1985
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Pólya, George
SC0337
40.5 Linear Feet
Papers relate to Pólya's research and teaching in mathematics and include professional and personal correspondence with mathematicians worldwide, 1910-1984; course materials including lecture notes; mathematical research notebooks dating from 1917 to 1960; manuscripts including those from his published works Complex Variables, How to Solve It, Mathematical Discovery, and Mathematics and Plausible Reasoning; ephemera; reprints; and photographs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The materials in this collection were given to Stanford University by Mrs. George Pólya in 1986, 1987, and 1988, and by Gerald L. Alexanderson, 1989-2009.
Information about Access
Materials in Subseries 8 of accession 1989-132 are restricted until January 1, 2039. Otherwise the collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Hungarian mathematician George Pólya was educated at the University of Budapest and the University of Paris, and taught at the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology in Zurich from 1914 to 1940. His students included future Stanford physics professors Felix Bloch and Hans Staub. In 1942 he joined Stanford's Department of Mathematics, whose chairman, Gábor Szegö, had been a fellow student in Hungary. He continued to teach until his 90th birthday in 1977. Following early research on probability, Pólya turned to the difficult area of the theory of functions of a complex variable. He was also interested in geometry and geometrical methods. His study of symmetry in the plane was studied and applied by the Dutch artist M.C. Escher. Pólya's later work on the principles of heuristics and problem solving is credited with providing a foundation for the application of computers to artificial intelligence. In addition to his own research and teaching, Pólya was concerned with methods of teaching mathematics and mathematics teachers. He is considered the father of the current trend toward emphasizing problem solving in mathematical teaching. His very successful book How to Solve It has been translated into fifteen languages and is still used widely. He died in 1985.
Description of the Collection
The papers in this collection relate to Pólya's research and teaching in mathematics and include professional and personal correspondence with mathematicians worldwide, 1910-1984; course materials including lecture notes; mathematical research notebooks dating from 1917 to 1960; manuscripts including those from his published works Complex Variables, How to Solve It, Mathematical Discovery, and Mathematics and Plausible Reasoning; ephemera; reprints; and photographs.
Mathematics -- Study and teaching.; Mathematics.; Riesz, Frigyes; Pólya, George; Schlesinger, Ludwig, b. 1864; Pólya, George; Runge, Carl; Schur, Issai; Schoenberg, I.J.; Montel, Paul, b.1876.; Mittag-Leffler, Magnus Gustaf; Norlund, Niels Erik; Nevanlinna, Rolf; Pfluger, Albert; Ostrowski, A.M. (Alexander M.); Pringsheim, Alfred; Prather, Carl.; Tietze, Heinrich; Toeplitz, Otto; von Pidoll, Max.; Beke, Manó; Weyl, Hermann; Wigner, Eugene Paul; Wirtinger, Wilhelm; Young, Grace Chisolm.; Siegel, Carl Ludwig; Sierpiński, Wacław; Sommerfeld, Arnold; Stanford University. Department of Mathematics. Faculty; Stern, Alfred.; Stáckel, Paul; Szász, Otto; Hardy, G.H. (Godfrey Harold); Harary, Frank.; Hadwiger, Hugo.; Hadamard, Jacques; Haar, Alfréd; Frege, Gottlob; Fekete, Mihaly; Fejér, Lipót.; Edrei, Albert.; De Finetti, Bruno.; Carathéodory, Constantin; Brentano, Franz Clemens; Borel, Émile; Bohr, Harold; Alexanderson, Gerald L.; Bieberbach, Ludwig; Szegő, Gábor; Bernays, Paul; Lehmer, D.H. (Derrick Henry); Littlewood, John E. (John Edensor); Kollros, Louis; Landau, Edmund; Kiefer, Albert; Kamke, E. (Erich); Knuth, Donald Ervin; Keszthelyi, Tibor, Dr.; Hurwitz, Adolf; Jentzsch, Robert; Hille, Einar; Hirsch, Arthur; Higgins, Thomas James.; Hilbert, David; Hecke, Erich; Hensel, Kurt
- Papers, Accession ARCH-1986-036
  - Draft: Chapter One: Polanyi Biography Summer 1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript: Problems and Solutions (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Course Outlines: Math 110, Math 129: How to Solve the Problem (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Draft: How To Solve It (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Early Manuscript of Mathematical Discovery. The Aims; Part I: Patterns; Chapter 1: Patterns of 2 Loci; Chapter 2: The Cartesian Pattern; Chapter 3: Recursion; Chapter 6: Widening the Scope; Solutions (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Pages 2-4, 7, 11 of Typed Manuscript, Essay. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Part 2 of Manuscript. Patterns of Plausible Inference; Chapter 12: Some Conspicuous Patterns. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Manuscript. Preface, Hints to the Reader, Bibliography, Contents, Outline of Chapters. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Manuscript. Chapter 1. Induction and Analogy. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Manuscript. Chapter 2: Generalization, Specialization, Analogy. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Manuscript. Chapter 3. Induction in Solid Geometry. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Manuscript. Chapter 4. Induction in Theory of Numbers. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Manuscript. Chapter 5. Misc. Examples of Induction. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Manuscript. Chapter 6. A More General Statement. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Manuscript. Chapter 7. Mathematical Induction. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Manuscript. Chapter 8. Minima and Maxima. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Manuscript. Chapter 9. Physical Mathematics. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Manuscript. Chapter 10. The Isoperimetric Problem. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Manuscript. Chapter 11. Kinds of Plausible Reasons. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Manuscript. Chapter 12. Further Patterns and First Links. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Manuscript. Chapter 14. Chance, the Ever-present Rival Conjecture. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Manuscript. Chapter 15. The Calculus of Probability and the Logic of Plausible Reasoning. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Manuscript. Chapter 16. Plausible Reasoning in Invention and Instruction. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Mathematical Discovery Manuscript; Supplement to Bibliography; Miscellaneous Sections (Typed); Contents: Chapters 7-15; Chapter 7; Chapter 8; Chapter 9; 3 Pages of Chapter 10. Chapter 11; Chapter 12 (4th Copy). (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Mathematical Discovery Manuscript. Chapter 13; Pamphlet "On Learning, Teaching, and Learning Teaching"; Chapter 14; Chapter 15; Chapter 1. Mathematical Language; Chapter 2. Beginnings of Integral Calculus. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Third Essay: Some Notions of Logic; I: The Notions and the Notations; III: Logical Links between the Proposed Problem and Its Auxiliary Problems. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Mathematical Discovery in the Classroom. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Course Descriptions for Math 110, Physical Sciences 115; Course Notes for Math 129; Part 1: Some Problems on Maxima and Minia in Elementary Geometry. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Handwritten Notes: A Simple Method of Approximation Applicable to Some Problems. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Crystallography. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Equations (1 page) (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Pages 116-193 of Typed Manuscript. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Designons par le Perimetre et par v le Rayon Conforme Exterieur d'Une Courbe. La Premiere des Deux Inequalites (2 pages) (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - An Isoperimetric Inequality for Convex Curves (3 pages). Analyse Mathematique (6 pages. (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Term Paper Assignments. (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Aufgaben Und Lehrsatze Aus der Analysis. 3 Excerpts. Pages 123-131, 156-159, 378-379. Techniques for Planning the Small Experimental Project. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - A Generalization of the Theorem on the Capacity of a Condenser. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Exam Book. Equations, Theorems, Proofs (30 pages). Approximations to the Area of the Ellipsoid (30 pages). (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Areas of Ellipsoid (11 pages). (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Memoires Presentes par Divers Savants a L'Academie des Sciences (1 page). Page 29-C of Tables. 4 Figures. (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Equations/Tables (8 pages) (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Tables (30 pages) (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Equations (8 pages); Torsional Rigidity Increases by Symmetrization (1 page); Equations (3 pages); De Saint-Venant (2 pages). (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Problems (29 pages) (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Manuscript of Solutions to Vol. I of Mathematics and Plausible Reasoning. Chapter 1 Solutions. (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Chapter 2 Solutions (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Chapter 3 Solutions (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Chapter 4 Solutions (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Chapter 5 Solutions (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Chapter 6 Solutions (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Chapter 7 Solutions (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Chapter 8 Solutions (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Chapter 9 Solutions (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Chapter 10 Solutions (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Chapter 11 Solutions (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Chapter 12 Solutions (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Chapter 13 Solutions (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Chapter 14 Solutions (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Chapter 15 Solutions (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Chapter 16 Solutions (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Problem Solving Seminar: 1963; term papers, mid-terms (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Math 129: How to Solve the Problem, course outlines, term papers, mid-term examinations, final examinations (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript: Circle, Spheres, Symmetricals and Some Classical Physical Problems (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Manuscript: Preface to Mathematical Discovery (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Reprint: On Functions of Sequences of Independent Chance Vectors with Applications to the Problems of the "Random Walk" in k Dimensions, by Blackwell, D. and Girshick, M.A.; miscellaneous notes (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Mathematical notes: On the Zeros of Successive Derivatives (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Draft: Complex Variables, by Pólya, George and Latta, G.E. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Project with Peter? Desordre (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Draft: Complex Variables, By Pólya, George and Latta, G.E. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Remarks on Certain Aspects of Some Processes, Resembling to and Differing from the Poisson-Process, by Binet, F.E. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Draft: Complex Variables, by Pólya, George and Latta, G.E. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Final Exam for Math 187-b (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Class Roll Books; Class Lists; NSF Summer Institute for High School Teachers of Mathematics 1972; Group Photo 1969 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - NSF Summer Institute for High School Teachers of Mathematics 1966, 1967. Class Lists and Addresses (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Math 111-S Final Summer 1965; Math 187-C Final July 29, 1965; Shell Fellows 1967 List; Math 111-S Final - Parts 1,2, Summer 1967; The Mathematics Curriculum (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Seminar on Solving Math Problems 1966: Notes Jan-May 1966; Dept. of Mathematics Graduate Students Office Directory Winter 1966; Memo from Webb to Freshman Seminar Instructors (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Competitive Examination in Math: Solutions and Comments 1951-1956, 1958, 1964-1965; Meeting of Math Association of America, Aug. 20, 1956; Meeting of National Council of Teachers of Mathematics, Aug. 21 1956: Minutes/Speeches (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Letters to Winners and Alternates of Stanford-Sylvania Competitive Exam in Math; Announcement on Competitive Exam March 1963, Instructions (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 1954, 1956-1958, 1961, 1963 Exams (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Los Angeles Mathematics Newsletter April 1956 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Math Contest Sponsored by Metropolitan New York Section of the Math Association of America 1950-1952 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Committee on Contests and Awards Releases 1951 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence Pólya-Boyer 1951 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - The National Status of Math Contests in Secondary Schools (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - National Council of Teachers of Math (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Henry L. Alder Letter (Co-Chairman of Committee on Contests) (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Report on the Math Contests held in Northern California (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Information on the Contest (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Letters from Henry L. Alder (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Registration for 1956 Annual Math Contest (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Rules of the 1956 Annual Contest (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Awards (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Henry L. Alder Letter to Chairmen of Dept. of Math (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Letter from Pólya to Prof. W. H. Fagerstrom, Jan. 23, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Letter from Pólya to Prof.John C. Schoonmaker, Nov. 23, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Letter from John C. Schoonmaker to Pólya, Oct. 29, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Pólya to John C. Schoonmaker, Nov. 8, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - John C. Schoonmaker to Pólya, March 25, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Reply by Pólya's Secretary (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - John C. Schoonmaker to Pólya, Nov. 12, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Pi Mu Epsilon Contest and Solutions, March 13, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Emory P. Starke to Pólya, May 29, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Emory P. Starke to Gabor Szego, April 23, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Math Prize Test, New Brunswick, NJ, April 25, 1953. State Math Day Program (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Emory P. Starke to Gabor Szego, June 30, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Gabor Szego to Emory P. Starke, July 7, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Students' Assignments (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Math 188-A Final, Summer 1966 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Shell Merit Fellows List, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - NSF Summer Institute for High School Teachers of Math: 1965 List (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Academic Year Institute for High School Teachers of Chemistry and Math 1960-61 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Instructor's End Quarter Grade Report for Math 111-S, Summer 1966 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Shell Merit Fellows Summer 1966 Directory (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Final for Math 111-S, Aug. 11, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Mid-term and End-Quarter Report for Math 188-A, April, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Pólya's Notes/Grades for Math 187-C (NSF) and Math 111-S (Shell), Summer 1965 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Final for Math 187-C, July 29, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - The Mathematical Log, September 1958 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - High School Math Contest Student Answerbook (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letters to Pólya and Szego, April 25, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letter to Pólya from Murray S. Klamkin, April 22, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letter to M. Gail Adams from F.R. Watson, Dec. 21, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letter from Adams to Watson, Dec. 9, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letter from Watson to Adams, Nov. 23, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letter from Virginia S. Boles to Watson, March 30, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letter from Watson to Boles, Aug. 24, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letter from Woolum to Boles, Oct. 19, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Letter from Boles to Woolum, Oct. 6, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Watson to Math. Department, April 9, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Boles to Watson, July 29, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Boles to Watson, Nov. 9, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Problems and Solutions for 1960 Stanford-Sylvania Competitive Exam in Math by Pólya (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Stanford Competitive Exam in Math, 1946-1964; Article on Exam, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Exams, 1946-1964 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Mathematikai Lapoh. Budapest, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Letter to Pólya from James H. McKay, Feb. 14, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Pamphlet and Typed Speeches on the Stanford University Math Examination, 1946 (2 copies) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Pamphlet "A Look at Mathematical Competitions", March 1959 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Exams, 1947-1948, 1950-1953 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Letter from Edwin Eagle to Pólya, April 5, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Letter from Eagle to Szego, March 20, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Letter from Szego to Eagle, April 9, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 1954 Exam Solutions, Written and Typed (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Letter from Boles to Eagle, April 14, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Letter from Boles to J.D. Wilson, July 5, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 1956 Exam Solution, Hand-written (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 1956 Results (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 1957 Exam and Solutions, Remarks, Results (2 Copies) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 9-Math, 10-Math, 11-Math by Pólya (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 1956 Exam and Solutions (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 1949 Exam - Problems and Results (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "On the Mathematics Curriculum of the High School" (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "Analyse Mathematique", Institut de France, 3 pgs. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - The California Mathematics Council Bulletin, Fall, 1961, Oct. 1960 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "Ten Commandments for Teachers" (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "On the Ratio of Consecutive Eigenvalues" (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - The Mathematical Log, Jan. 1960 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Nieuw Archief Voor Wiskunde (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "Bounds for Eigenvalues of Pólya's 'Plane-Covering Domains' by Filling a Top of a Cylinder" by Hersch (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "Pólya's Contributions to Chemical Enumerations" by Harary, Palmer and Robinson (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "An Extension of Pólya's Theorem on Power Series With Integer Coefficients" by Robinson (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "Hadamard Products of Schlicht Functions and the Pólya-Schoenberg Conjecture" by Ruscheweyh and Sheil-Small (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "Pólya's Enumeration Formula by Example" by Tucker (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Letter from Andrew F. Acker to Pólya, Feb. 21, 1977, and Enclosures (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Letter from Sami Beraha to Pólya, Aug. 18, 1961, and Enclosures (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Letters from Albert Edrei to Pólya, March 29, 1978, April 16, 1978, April 26, 1978, and Enclosures (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Letter from Doris Schattschneider to Pólya, Sept. 13, 1977 Plus Photograph of Escher's Writing (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Letter from W. Wm. Funkenbusch to Pólya, May 29, 1979 and Paper (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Letter from Frank Harary to Pólya, March 16, 1978 with "From Euler's Partitions to Cayley's Rooted Trees" by Harary; Letter from Barnabas B. Hughes to Pólya, July 21, 1977 with "A Study in Medieval Problem Solving" (2 Copies) (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Letter from Donald E. Knuth to Pólya, Aug. 16, 1976; Various Calculations; Letter from Jean (?) to Pólya, Aug. 10, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Letter from Thomas James Higgins to Pólya, Nov. 14, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Calculations (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - "Experimental Determination of the Capacitance of Heavy-Current Busses Comprised of Solid or Tubular Rectangular Conductors" by Teasdale and Higgins (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Letter from Higgins to Pólya, Aug. 20, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Letter from Higgins to Pólya, May 21, 1947 and Enclosure. (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Pólya's Reply, June 24, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Postcard from Higgins to Pólya, June 30, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Letter from Higgins to Pólya, June 28, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Letters from D.H. Lehmer to Pólya, April 27, 1943, May 10, 1943 and Enclosures on "Inequalities for the Area of the Ellipsoid" (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Postcard DHL to Pólya, February 1943 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Letter DHL to Pólya, Feb. 1, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Letter DHL to Pólya, Fe. 9, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Letter from Lehmer to Pólya, April 20, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Letter from Lehmer to Pólya, May 26, 1943 and Enclosures (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Letter from Lehmer to Pólya, Dec. 23, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Letter from Lehmer to Pólya, July 11, 1943 and Enclosures (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Letter from Lehmer to Pólya, July 18, 1943 and Enclosure (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Letter from Lehmer to Pólya, July 20, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - "A Simpler Theory of the Mathematical Infinite" by Arthur Marystone with Letter to Pólya (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Letter from Donald A. McQuarrie to Pólya, March 31, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Letters from Carl Prather to Pólya, June 2, 1978, March 28, 1978, March 3, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - "A Note on an Extension of the Asymptotic Formula for the Bell Numbers" by Prather (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Draft of Pólya Letter to Prather, July 4, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Letter from Sister Madeleine Rose to Pólya, Undated and Enclosed Preliminary Draft of Dissertation Proposal (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Information and Instructions on Experiment (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - "The Use of Heuristic Methods for Problem Solving in Algebra" (Revised Proposal by Rose) (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - 3 Problems and Solutions (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Letters from I.J. Schoenberg to Pólya - undated (incomplete), May 30, 1970 and Enclosure (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Schoenberg Flow Chart on Problem Solving Model, Math 191-A Discussion; Letter from Schoenberg to Pólya, Oct. 25, 1977; "Can Heuristics be Taught?" by Schoenberg; Excerpt from Boole: Collected Works, Vol. 2 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Letter from Jack Williamson to Pólya, March 15, 1977 and Enclosures; Letter from John J. Wavrik to Pólya, Jan. 27, 1978 and Enclosures (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Letter from A.W. Heuberg to Pólya, Nov. 28, 1962; Letter from Alexander Wittenberg to Moise, Nov. 27, 1962; Letter from Philip H. Abelson to Wittenberg, Nov. 21, 1962; "Qui Aurait Pu Penser A Cela?" by Wittenberg (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - "Der Mathematische und NaturWissenschaftliche Unterricht" (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Identification and Development of the Mathematically Talented -- The Hungarian Experience, by Agnes Arrai Wieschenberg, PhD. Dissertation submitted to the School of Arts and Sciences, Columbia University, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Additional Papers, Accession ARCH-1989-132
  - Biographical, Subseries 1
    - George Pólya - Biographical, 1979-1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Biographical Notes, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Biographical - on Zurich and ETH, 1914, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Pólya Gyorgy, Stanford Egyetem (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Pólya Bibliography, circa 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Grade Books from Grammar Schools, 1893-1896 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Report Books After Grammar School, 1905-1912 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence about Teaching Posts and Lectures, 1920-1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Pólya’s Ph.D. Students and Collaborators (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Dissertations by Pólya Students, 1928-1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Pólya Mentioned (Egocentrics), 1974-1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Scope and Contents note
      Pólya labled this folder "Egocentrics."
    - Recommendations, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Two-Year College Mathematical Journal, 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Stanford Faculty Reports, 1965-1971 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - John Pólya, 1952-1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Various articles by and about Dr. John Pólya (brother?)
    - J.B. Pólya on Fluoridation, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Family, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, Subseries 2
    - Varia, 1934-1940 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Communications, 1930-1954 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1979-1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Miscelaneous Correspondence, 1981-1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Personal Correspondence, 1961-1966 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1971-1983 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1961-1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Alexander Israel Wittenberg, 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Alfred Renyi, Kato (Catherine) Renyi, Paul Erdos, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1919-1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Pólya Prize, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Permission Requests, 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Consulting Agreements and Requests, 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Stanford Library Archives, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Stella Pólya, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Reviews and Reports of Papers, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Class Materials, Subseries 3
    - Theory of Numbers, Problem Solving seminar (NSF), 1962-1967 (Box 2, Folder 17)